ACTWU's Subject Records 5619/020
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
ACTWU's Subject Records
1925-1995
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America
Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union
5619/020
3 cubic feet
3 linear feet
Correspondence, reports, publications.
This collection consists of subject files for Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America and Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers' Union. Arranged alphabetically for each union.
6766177
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff
Date completed:
February 17, 2010
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, July 2010
Biographical / Historical
The Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America, the most significant union representing workers in the men's clothing industry, was founded in New York City in 1914 as a breakaway movement from the United Garment Workers. Radical and immigrant workers in the tailors' and cutters' locals were the core of the seceding group, which advocated industrial unionism and economic strikes in opposition to the UGW's craft organization, which they saw as conservative and timid. Their diverging views had come to the fore during the historic 1910 dispute at the Chicago firm Hart, Schaffner, and Marx. The opposition called the strike against the UGW leadership's advice, and reached a path-breaking agreement with management that established an arbitration system to settle disputes.
Members flocked to the new union. Around 50,000 strong at its founding, by 1920 the ACWA counted about 170,000 members. Initially composed mostly of immigrants of Jewish European descent with Socialist leanings, the ACWA quickly welcomed members of a great number of nationalities and diverse backgrounds. Like in other garment unions, most workers and many members were women, but the leadership was predominantly male, a situation that did not change for many decades. Early on the union adopted a centralized administrative structure combined with industrial unionism, with the joint boards' by-laws having precedence over those of locals.
Espousing a philosophy perhaps brought over by its early immigrant socialist members, the Amalgamated went beyond bread and butter issues and adopted a distinctive form of social unionism that was largely absent in the American labor movement. Starting in the 1920s, it provided educational opportunities and recreational facilities for its members, as well as services such as an insurance plan, banks offering personal loans at low interest rates, low-cost housing cooperatives, medical clinics, and even union-owned restaurants.
Sidney Hillman was the first president of the new union and the most important officer in its history. He applied his experience as bargaining representative in Chicago to the whole industry. Under his leadership the union made significant strides in securing better wages and working conditions for its members, and at the same time it consolidated gains and provided stability to the industry through the widespread adoption of the arbitration system tested at Hart, Schaffner, and Marx. Hillman paid close attention to industry issues, such as production, pricing, and marketing. In order to help management meet the competition of non-union firms, the union conducted studies of efficiency, work methods, and factory costs. Letters to the official publication of the union, Advance, document the controversy that ensued within the union over what was perceived to be collaboration with management.
Hillman also understood the importance of labor's involvement in national affairs and political action. In the 1920s the ACWA sent delegates to the Conference for Progressive Political Action and to the Farmer-labor party conventions. Although many members and officers were Socialists, the union stopped short of officially endorsing the party. Communist attempts at gaining influence within the union were firmly curbed. Hillman's participation in national affairs and politics became prominent during the New Deal, when he became a close advisor to Franklin D. Roosevelt on labor and economic issues. He also served on the board of the National Recovery Administration. Later, during World War II, he helped establish the Labor's Non Partisan League. He was also named associate director of the Office of Production Management, which assisted in mobilizing the nation's resources for the war effort. Hillman's prestige perhaps reflected the healthy condition of his union, which by the end of the conflict was strong and stable.
During the post World War II period the union faced a number of significant challenges. Membership continued to grow (peaking at 395,000 in 1968), but the union's political influence and visibility in national affairs declined. In their never ending pursuit of lower production costs, many firms relocated to the South, forcing the union to engage in large organizing efforts. Simultaneously, signs began to appear of changes that would lead to the almost complete demise of the domestic apparel industry and, ultimately, to the erosion of union membership. Foreign imports of cheap clothing goods steadily grew in the 1950s and 1960s, and mushroomed in the following two decades, plunging employment in the apparel sector into a steady decline. Union efforts to stem the tide included Buy American campaigns and extensive lobbying in Congress, but they were to no avail. In 1976, the ACWA merged with the Textile Workers of America to become the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union. Despite successful and much publicized nationwide actions such as the Farah boycott and the J.P. Stevens corporate campaign, the woes threatening the union's existence continued unabated. The fate of the domestic industry was sealed in the late 1970s and the 1980s by the flight of firms chasing tax breaks and cheap labor abroad. By 1995, when ACTWU voted to merge with the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union, their combined membership was 350,000. The new Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees (UNITE!) seemed poised to infuse new life in a troubled union.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related collections: 5619: Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America And all other 5619 collections.
Textile workers--Labor unions--New York (State); Clothing workers--Labor unions--New York (State); Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union --Archives; Eaton Yale & Towne --Archives; Electrolux Group --Archives; Emerson Electric (Firm) --Archives; Flintkote Company --Archives; GAF Corporation --Archives; Globe-Union Incorporated --Archives; H.K. Porter Company --Archives; Harvey Hubbell, Inc. --Archives; Hercules Corporation --Archives; Hooker Chemical Corporation --Archives; Inmot Corporation --Archives; Interco, Inc. --Archives; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union --Archives; Johns-Manville Corporation --Archives; Johnson & Johnson --Archives; Kendall Company --Archives; Kidde, Inc. --Archives; Koppers Company --Archives; Leggett and Platt, Inc. --Archives; McGraw-Edison Company --Archives; Merck & Co. --Archives; Murray Corporation of America --Archives; National Gypsoum Company --Archives; Olin Corporation --Archives; Outboard Marine Corporation --Archives; Owens-Corning Fiberglas Corporation --Archives; Ozite Corporation --Archives; PPG Industries --Archives; Quaker Oats Company --Archives; Revere Copper and Brass Incorporated --Archives; Rexall Drug and Chemical Company --Archives; Rohm and Hass Company --Archives; Sealy Holdings, Inc. --Archives; Sheller Manufacturing Corporation --Archives; Singer Company --Archives; Stauffer Chemical Company --Archives; Textron, Inc. --Archives; Union Carbide Corporation --Archives; Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees (UNITE)--Archives; UNITE HERE (Organization) --Archives; United States Pipe and Foundry Company --Archives; United States. Occupational Safety and Health --Archives; W.R. Grace & Co. --Archives; Whirlpool Corporation --Archives
6766177
- ACTWU: Activities/Programs/Grants (Box 1, Folder 1)
- ACTWU: Amalgamated Service and Allied Industries Joint Board (Box 1, Folder 2)
- ACTWU: By-Laws (model form for local unions and joint board) (Box 1, Folder 3)
- ACTWU: Collective Bargaining/Banks/SLA's (Box 1, Folder 4)
- ACTWU: Companies using the ACTWU Union Label (Box 1, Folder 5)
- ACTWU: Companies where more than 1,000 employees are represented (Box 1, Folder 6)
- ACTWU: Cotton Garment Shops: Plant Average Earnings, Aug. 1994 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Scope and Contents
  August, 1994.
- ACTWU: Day care (Box 1, Folder 8)
- ACTWU: Denim Mills: Summary of Economic Benefits, 1/10/94, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  January 10, 1994.
- ACTWU: Elections and Recognitions in U.S. and Canada, by Jonit Board, 1983 - 1993. (Box 1, Folder 10)
- ACTWU: Employment at Plants (U.S.), by primary SIC, 3/21/1995 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  March 21, 1995.
- ACTWU: Establishments and Employees in Textile & Apparel Industries, by 4-digit SIC (U.S. and Canada), 3/31/95, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  March 31, 1995.
- ACTWU: Establishments and Employees, by state and province, 3/21/95, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- ACTWU: Member's Kit (Box 1, Folder 14)
- ACTWU: Membership by Geographical Region, 1977, 1986, 1994 (9/11/95), 1995 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  September 11, 1995.
- ACTWU: Organizing Conference: 9/15/1986 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  September 15, 1986.
- ACTWU: Plants that closed and shifted operations to Mexico, 10/31/91, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  October 31. 1991.
- ACTWU: Shoe workers - Merger (Box 1, Folder 18)
- ACTWU: Synthetic Fiber Plants: Contract Comparison (Box 1, Folder 19)
- ACTWU: Total Elections won 1982 - 1994; number of workers, by industry and year (Box 1, Folder 20)
- ACTWU: Trade Adjustment Assistance (Box 1, Folder 21)
- ACTWU: Uniform and Work Wear Manufacturers and their Industrial Customers, 1/8/1992 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  January 8, 1992.
- ACTWU: United Hatters Merger (Box 1, Folder 23)
- ACTWU: Average Wages of Competitors of Greif, 8/26/1994 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  August 26, 1994.
- ACTWU: Workers covered under contract by region, 3/27/95, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  March 27, 1995.
- ACWA/ACTWU: politics (Box 1, Folder 26)
- ACWA: Bibliography [folder 1 of 2] (Box 1, Folder 27)
- ACWA: Bibliography [folder 2 of 2] (Box 1, Folder 28)
- ACWA: Credit Unions (Box 1, Folder 29)
- ACWA: Constitutions and by-laws [folder 1 of 2] (Box 1, Folder 30)
- ACWA: Constitutions and by-laws [folder 2 of 2] (Box 1, Folder 31)
- ACWA: Directories (Box 1, Folder 32)
- ACWA: Education, 1973-1976 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- ACWA: General Descriptive Material (Box 1, Folder 34)
- ACWA: Glove Workers - merger (Box 1, Folder 35)
- ACWA: History, 1940-1959 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- ACWA: History, 1970-1979 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- ACWA: History, 1980-1989 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- ACWA: membership (Box 2, Folder 2)
- ACWA: membership (national) (Box 2, Folder 3)
- ACWA: membership (by age and sex) (Box 2, Folder 4)
- ACWA: membership (by ethnic group) (Box 2, Folder 5)
- ACWA: membership (by industry branch) (Box 2, Folder 6)
- ACWA: membership (geographic) (Box 2, Folder 7)
- ACWA: merger with TWU (Box 2, Folder 8)
- ACWA: Textile Workers Union, Merger Clips, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- ACWA: Pension Plans (Box 2, Folder 10)
- ACWA: Research Department (Box 2, Folder 11)
- ACWA: Staff retirement plan (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Amalgamated Bank of New York - Financial Statements, 1952-1996 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Amalgamated Bank, merger clippings, 1950-1959 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Amalgamated Bank, clippings, 1960-1965 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Amalgamated Bank, clippings, 1966-1972 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Amalgamated Bank, clippings, 1973-1978 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Amalgamated Bank, clippings, 1980-1983 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Amalgamated Bank, clippings, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Amalgamated Education, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Amalgamated Housing, 1928-1959 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Amalgamated Housing, 1960-1969 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Amalgamated Housing, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Amalgamated Housing, co-op city, Bronx, 1973-1977 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Amalgamated Trust and Savings; Chicago/Financial statements, 1950-1963 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Amalgamated Trust and Savings; Chicago/Financial statements, 1965-1966 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Annual payments toward group insurance for bargaining unit employees; ACTWU southern textiles, prior to 1986 wage movement (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Automotive Airbag and Component Plants, 9/15/93, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  September 15, 1993.
- Average compensation of ACTWU workers at Southern Textile Co., 1981-1988 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  Spring 1981, January 1988- December 1988
- Big Units Target Unit (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Education Fund Plan: Chicago, 1971-1973 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Establishments and Employees under contract with UNITE, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  June, 1996.
- Department of Social Services, 1973-1975 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Labor - banks (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Labor Unions - jurisdiction (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Labor Unions: United Hatters, Cap and Millinery Workers International (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Merger - Working Papers (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Merger and convention clippings (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Mexican plants of ACTWU companies in Auto Parts Industry, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  June 22, 1994.
- Philadelphia Scholarship Fund, 1971-1973 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Productivity and Real Earnings: Apparel and Textile Industries, 1955-1992, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  February 1, 1996.
- Profile of Auto Parts Industry, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  March 1, 1994.
- Sample Loom/Weaver Ratios at ACTWU Weaving Mills, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  June 10, 1992.
- Selected Auto Parts Companies, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  June 15, 1994.
- Social Service Department, 1975-1977 (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Story of the Amalgamated Clothing Workers Union and its People (Box 3, Folder 24)
- Survey of ACWTU "Cotton Garment" shops: brand names and customers, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  August 19, 1994.
- Tailored Clothing Research Project (preliminary report), 1993 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  July 21, 1993.
- Tailored Clothing Industry: Survey Report, Plants Under ACTWU contract, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  July 28, 1993.
- Textile and Apparel Employment and Real Hourly Earnings (chart), 1947-1993 (Box 3, Folder 28)
- UNITE Distribution Centers: Summary of Wages and Benefits, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  November 21, 1995.